welcome to the monthly Q&A it's a great
pleasure to be here again thank you very
much for joining the first thing I'd
like to do is mention that with Daniel
Drake I'm beginning and IndieGoGo
campaign to raise some money he and I
are working on a book the cognitive
continuum from insight to enlightenment
I'm not getting any salary or money out
of the book the point of that campaign
is to help finance Daniel who's gonna be
sort of working full-time on many
aspects of the book so that he can
decrease the time that it's going to
take to get it out into the public so
that campaign is up now it's available
there's a short video out on it that
I've tweeted about and there will be a
longer video coming out I believe today
or tomorrow in which Daniel I discuss a
greater length the content of the book
what the books trying to do how it links
up with the work I do the work I've done
on in this series awakening from the
meaning crisis the work I'm going to be
doing and not the after Socrates series
so please take a look at that as I said
one more time I'm not getting any
personal income out of this campaign or
out of the book it's going towards
supporting Daniel and he undertakes the
job of working on it doing some of the
writing a lot of the promotional work
developing a lot of the art etc so let's
turn to some of the questions I've
already had a Quick Looks with some of
them I just want to make an overall
comment I'm very appreciative of the
quality of the conversations that I'm
receiving it it's it's impressive
the insight and the acumen that people
are bringing to bear and so thank you
very much for that so the first question
is from patreon supporter Felix the
question those hi Jon with reference to
Leigh coughs work to what extent do you
think our imagination or experience or
determine
by being body beings and with reference
to Christopher that's Christopher master
Pietro and guy that's guys in stock the
inventor of circling to Christopher and
indice st. stocks we got conversation
regarding the bowing of the world do you
think we are determined as body beings
to seeing the world itself as body or
bodies many thanks as always for your
fantastic work Thank You first of all
Felix for your kind words so let's let's
take there's a couple of things in there
let's take them bit by bit
the first one is lake off the work of
like off often in conjunction with
Johnson Lake often Johnston so some of
you may know this because I mentioned it
in the video series I could work with
John Kennedy in in the 90s and the early
noughties
critiquing not just criticizing but
critiquing the work of Lake often
Johnson and the idea that our abstract
cognition is deeply influenced by the
fact that we are embodied in Vedic
beings was one of the central ideas so
to give you know a famous example that I
talked about in the in the series and
there was the central example of their
first big book metaphors we live by we
tend to talk about philosophical
abstract argumentation using the
language of war like he attacked my
position or I defended my position or he
undermined what I was trying to say etc
and then the idea is because we're
embodied beings we make use of our
fundamental way of making sense of the
world is embodied interaction and we
create these patterns and then we use
those patterns like in order to create
patterns of intelligibility for more
abstract domains now I think the idea
that conceptual thought abstract
conceptual thought is in some sense
grounded in sensory motor interaction I
think that's an important one I think
it's a pivotal thesis of what's called
4e cognitive science Tversky Barbour
Tversky the famous Tversky of Kahneman
Tversky has a new book out all mind in
motion
where she thought tries to argue very
deeply in John Kennedy and I made a very
similar argument in 2004 that a lot of
our thinking is ultimately grounded in
the fact that we're spatial and that we
are navigating through space and that we
use all of these spatial relations and
our navigational skills and our
perspective all awareness in you know
the three-dimensional lives space in
order to inform constrain and render
intelligible a lot of our abstract
thought and so I think all of this I
think is central like I think it goes
back altum Utley to the just seminal
work of merleau-ponty the phenomenology
of perception and which has deeply
informed for ich oxide so I think the
phenomena of the rounding relationship
between intelligence and embodiment I
think that is deeply right I argue for
example in my work on relevance
realization that it is the bile economic
constraints of the body that actually
put the constraints on the problem space
in problem-solving that actually afford
us being adaptive intelligent beings so
that if we if our brains weren't
embodied I don't even know what that
could light would mean it's maybe some
sort of disembodied computer thing but
if our brains were not if our brains did
not have to be regulated by cost
functions that our bio economic in
nature they would not have their
adaptive functionality and this lines up
with a lot of the arguments are made of
our relevance realization the fact that
in AI they're increasingly talking about
the important role of cost functions etc
so all of that is you know the ways in
which there's deep agreement with Lake
often Johnson but John and I also had
criticisms of Lake often Johnson because
we tend to argue that they saw the
relation as very is very simplistic and
to bottom up that all that's happening
is there's it's very it's in fear you'll
allow me a bit of a stretch their idea
is that the abstract mind is type it
aroused
just an empty slate and then
sensorimotor behavior writes on it and
then that's what gives us our you know
abstract conceptual thought and this is
this is shared with Piaget and the
there's in both empirical evidence and
argumentation to say that's not right
there's a lot of intrinsic constraints
within abstract space it's not a blank
slate it has lots of things going on
there that constrain which of all of
these interim you know interactional
sensory motor patterns get taken up or
how very different sensory motor
interactional patterns can be taken up
for the same abstract meaning i point
this out that will say i see what you're
saying in order to talk about
understanding we use understanding which
by the way was original right so notice
that grasping so another seeing standing
like standing within standing under
grasping all of these different sensory
motor things are somehow all being used
for the same abstract thing
well what draws these ver what selects
from all of my sensory motor patterns
those ones and why why are there
differences the differences between them
ignored and how is that they can all
point to something unless there was a
serious set of constraints there in the
first place so in addition to the bottom
up there's top-down and I've proposed
that the way we can make sense of that
is through a more recent idea from
Michael Anderson about cognitive
exaptation that we can take sensory
motor processes and they can be exact
'add but when they are exactly they have
new functions and new abilities they're
not simply mapped in a bottom-up fashion
there's also top-down constraints in
terms of you know the field
I'm exacting it into it I take this
sensory motor pattern and then I'm
exacting it into a new domain and that
new domain puts huge constraints and in
a top-down abstract fashion it
re-engineers
just like I'm using my tongue for speech
even though it evolved for taste and
moving the food around in my mouth so
this helps to explain why a lot of those
words that I used at the beginning he
attacked my argument don't quite
the sensorimotor demeaning John and I
pointed this out in 96 we pointed out
well yeah you can say he attacked my
position but notice other words that I
could use when I'm attacking a castle
like we assaulted or stormed the castle
don't really work as well
you wouldn't say in a philosophical
argument he assaulted my my argument
that that's fix people is weird or odd
or notice you can't transfer backwards
you can't you know because one of the
synonyms for he attacked my position is
he criticized my position now unless
we're doing a Monty Python routine you
can't use that as you know as a synonym
for attacking the castle you know let us
criticize the castle it doesn't really
convey let's attack the council and try
to destroy it
see so there's there's it's a much more
complex relation and there's a lot more
I can say about this the point I'm
trying to make is I think the embodiment
issue is correct and deeply grateful to
lay coffin johnson for bringing that out
I think the cognitive processes at work
are much more sophisticated much more
dynamical much more self-organizing
having a lot more to do with this idea
of exaptation then simply the straight
mapping of what lay Kevin Johnson called
image schemata now that goes towards
your second point do we have to see the
world as a body I'm not I'm not sure
that that's the case precisely because
as I just tried to show we don't map all
or you know maybe even some of the
central properties of our embodied
patterns up into our abstract conceptual
and theoretical space so I think it's
quite possible that we may have to see
the world in maybe some fundamental
terms that have to be shared are
continuous with our sensory motor
interaction but I do think that it's
possible to see reality not as a body
they're of course famous traditions that
argue this deeply or the Neoplatonic
tradition in the ancient West for
example in which was very explicit that
you had to leave thinking in Kippur
terms behind to get at the truth deaths
of the world what was ultimately the
case of a reality so I hope that answers
that very excellent question it was is a
complex question and and I point you to
some of the episodes in the in the
awakening for the meaning crisis where I
try to tackle it very deeply great
so here oh hello this is this is from
McKenzie Levin hi it's good to hear from
you a patreon supporter thank you very
much
here's your question do you think our
culture will eventually adopt a
widespread development and use of wisdom
institutions ah there's two there's two
ways I can turb for that question what I
predict that it's going to happen no it
ceteris paribus I don't think so I think
our culture is awash in some very
large-scale patterns of and
foolishness that are making change very
intractable this is this is my best
explanation for why we're not making the
transformations we need to save the
planet and to save our civilization and
to save our social institutions now the
question might ask is it possible with
our efforts and with a lot of teamwork
that we could make that transformation
yes I do think so so what I want to
avoid is any sense of complacency in
answering that question and in a
positive manner I think unless we work
really hard really concerted and really
smart I don't think we're going to get
that transition to where our culture has
widespread development of wisdom
institutions I think it is rational to
hope for such a thing and to work and
therefore to work hard for it and also
rational to believe that if we
seed that could contribute significantly
not solely but could could contribute
significantly to addressing these other
urgent and existentially threatening
problems that we're facing so thank you
very much for that question this is from
an anonymous patreon supporter any New
Year's resolutions that's an odd
question I don't make new year's
resolutions I sort of understand why
people do it I guess the the the
symbolic turning of the year is was
supposed to be an auspicious time to
trying something new so I understand the
symbolism so I in order to answer the
question honestly I would say something
like what might I resolve to do but then
I suppose I wouldn't try and hinge it on
some pivotal moment of resolution
because the evidence shows that that's
largely ineffective for transforming
people's behavior what I've intent
instead tried to do is create a strategy
in which behaviors are adopted initially
very sort of locally somewhat
superficially and then they start to
permeate of their own accord through the
rest of my life
so for example I took up the practice of
trying to record at the end of the day
any of the cognitive biases that I had
noticed throughout the day is a way of
trying to Train active open mindedness
and increase my rationality but what has
happened in a way that is exemplary or
yeah exemplary of this kind of thing
happening in many other places is that
practice has taken on a life of its own
it started to grow the journal is now
almost has a perspective of presence for
me I often noticed things because it's
almost like I become aware because I
think oh what would my
think about that which is kind of this
interesting personification but you know
because it's like what Socrates said is
but he's gonna face this person no
matter what when he goes home at night
namely the Socrates that's gonna be
asked him to reflect on his day and also
what's happened is I've started to write
content in my journal other than just
the cognitive biases I started to notice
more pervasive patterns and existential
modes that might be contributing to the
self-deception so a weight this is
interesting because you know the
Buddhists talked about this if I you
know drop by drop you fill up the jar is
so I start this very sort of easy to do
practice right but I and you know that I
located it on a you know regular time
regular space so it's just repeated and
then what happens is a lot of these
practices just don't take and I
understand that's the case but there
seems to be a way of getting them so
they start to take on a life of their
own
and they start to permeate and presents
themselves in your life and in your
reflective awareness in a more
comprehensive fashion they sort of
percolate which seems to me to be a much
more successful strategy than sort of
the resolve to attempts that seem to be
the prototypical thing you do for new
year's resolutions so I found that a
much better strategy in general for
trying to transfer my behavior generally
try and find a habit that is easy to
start but has this potential to grow of
its own accord and take on a life of its
own and then sort of percolate and
permeate through your life in your
cognition I found that a much more
successful strategy so that's how I
would answer that question I hope that's
ople to people okay so the next is from
a patreon supporter Sergey marker Kent
giving the importance of wisdom for
increasing personal and public good it
seems a good idea to work on increasing
personal wisdom what do you think about
the possibility and means of pushing or
nudging or even forcing someone to work
on increasing her wisdom
ah so that's an interesting question
because I have two different populations
that I've interacted with around that
issue that have given me two very
different sort of results and therefore
have led me to a very similar conclusion
one is when I've worked with my students
and I was actually talking about this
yesterday in a lecture and of course I'm
teaching on the psychology of wisdom
about what you're actually trying to do
is induce aspiration two people by
trying to set up an agave for them if
you can set up an agar game where you
give them a bit of resolving inner
conflict and anxiety so they can see a
little bit more clearer and then they
start to realize some patterns start to
see through some illusions start to
break you know inappropriate framing and
then they get better sort of
experiencing real patterns they get
better at realizing and then they can
turn that back onto themselves and if
you start to sort of enact with them
Anna Gauguin get that going then that
can actually help them to overcome the
aspiration paradox they cannot because
you can't infer your way through it but
you can sort of an agog your way through
it and then and then of course as I
argued elsewhere that requires you
actually give them you know inactive
analogies that sort of point back to the
life they're leading and forward to the
life they're going into and I think and
we talked about this in class this has
serious overlaps with techniques that
you use with in therapy I think you can
do that now that counts as nudging I
think you can nudge people in that way
and that's all I would ever try and do
within an academic situation because I'm
dealing with autonomous adults who I do
not have any authority over other than
scholastic Authority and with my
children it's a different thing because
I have parental authority over them and
I'm trying to do something much more
profound and I have permission in fact I
have obligation to intervene to
intervene and perhaps interfere
intervene in their lives in a much more
profound manner and what what happens
there is I have realized how often I
have foolishly mistaken the thought that
I've been foolish ly mistake
in thinking that I could push people
into wisdom
trying to push my sons to be more wise
has often had the opposite effect so
there's been significant failure on my
part and I tried to learn from that it
points me back to paying more attention
to how much implicit narcissism and
hubris can haunt even our what we think
are even our noblest goals so that's an
important thing I I don't know if
anybody other than a god this is
Socrates's idea has the wisdom to try
and push wisdom on to anybody else
that's what I'm concluding for that what
seems to have worked with my older son
my younger son is 15 and he's still of
course in transition in profound ways
but seems to have worked with my older
son who is becoming a just an incredibly
decent and good person what seems to
work more with him is living an example
and trying to invite him into aspects of
my life and having shared interests so
that in a way that it was talking that
similar to what I was talking about
resolutions he starts to catch little
things little habits little ways of
thinking little ways of redirecting
problems ways of maybe improving
studying solving this he starts to catch
those and then what starts to permeate
and percolate is right something that
starts to take on a life of its own and
what's awakening in him now is the
personal aspiration towards wisdom so
that's what I think is the the best
advice that I can give in terms of what
I've concluded from both where I've
succeeded and where I've drastically
failed and how you can try and if I'm
trying to use this as a neutral verb
lead people to wisdom when which I'll or
whatever wisdom I might possess and as I
also argued you in Thursday on Thursday
I think one of the sure signs that
someone is not wise as if they claim to
be because wisdom is I think this is one
of the profound truths and I don't have
time to talk about how profound it is we
are always philosophers which means
lovers of wisdom wisdom is something
that is always something we're aspiring
to it is always how we are evolving
always how we're developing so I hope
it's understood that in everything I
said about nudging people towards wisdom
that I'm speaking as a lover of wisdom
and not as someone who is claiming to be
wise the next question is from the
patreon supporter betterment project
seems like an appropriate segue from
what we were just talking about so thank
you very much for your support can you
detail why it is that existing religions
do not hold the answers to the meaning
crisis from your perspective now that's
that I want to answer that question in
sort of a slow step-by-step fashion
because and I don't tribute any any
incorrect and intent from the questioner
but there's two ways in which you can be
asking a question do I think let's do
one way do I think that individual
people can find in the existing
religions ways to cultivate wisdom and
self transcendence yes I do so I might
have answered that question well say
that actually I don't think it's true
that the existing religions can't give
responses to the meaning crisis I think
that they can for certain people I've
met these people it would be dishonest
for me to claim that individual people
do not find ways are within the existing
religions to cultivate wisdom and self
transcendence
if that's what you're looking for that
clearly happens what I do I want to make
I do want to make a comment that I
noticed that those people have a
transformative relationship to those
religions they don't simply sort of
adopt the religions sort of as in the
classic Orthodox form they're often
interpreting and
forming them in powerful ways so if
that's what we're talking about I think
it is possible for the individual
religion to do that now let's talk about
what we might be asking do I think that
oh do I see these people as fine as
they're finding their individual
responses to meaning the threat of
meaning loss of their rods are they also
cultivating answers to how that was
meaning making projects can be safely
rehomed within a scientific worldview
that is at what would otherwise be at
best dismissive of them or is usually
critical or deconstructive of them what
I don't see in the existing religions or
in these people that I otherwise have
deep respect for and I want that
remembered please is I don't see an
answer to those problems I often see
like I'm not normally think about the
science or maybe a little bit of it I'm
gonna resist the science in some way I
find that problematic here's why I find
that problematic I take very deeply
Heidegger's point that the scientific
worldview is deeply woven into every
fabric of our cultural cognitive grammar
and in our life because here's what
Heidegger part of what Heidegger was
arguing when we talk about science we
don't mean the abstract theories alone
inside the ivory towers of academia we
mean the way in which we have an
ontology folded around that folded
around us supporting every aspect of us
that's technology technology is the
embodiment of a scientific worldview so
it's kind of strange for somebody to say
for example while they're on YouTube
while they're using computers right I
don't really accept the scientific
worldview that's a performative
contradiction that doesn't make any
sense
ultimately like you all you deeply
accept it unless you sum it all unless
you just sort of I don't know but
thinking that the the you
what am i hesitating to say I don't want
to be insulting but if you think that
this technology somehow not dependent on
our science and the hyper technology
that's happening right now is steep so
deeply enmeshed and this and the
technology feeds back and enables the
science they are deeply wedded together
and they surround and permeate our
environment our work our communication
about how we make use of almost all
aspects of our cognition they give us
terms and ways of thinking and people
talk about you know hardware and
software whether real art like that's
what I'm talking about ok so the idea
that we can somehow neglect the task of
resituated meaning making within a
scientific worldview strikes me as not
existentially viable of course of course
people should and I engage in
discussions with people who do this make
philosophical criticisms of particular
scientific theories that should be done
that should be done that should always
be done that's very different from
trying to say I'll just sort of reject a
scientific worldview that strikes me as
not existentially viable for us so I
don't see the existing religions on sort
of on mass again there is probably
individual theologians if that's a broad
enough term for the you know
philosophical intellectuals within the
existing religions right there are
probably individual theologians who are
wrestling with this I have read some of
them but do I see the institutions or
wrestling with how do we reinter great
the psycho technologies and the
practices of wisdom and meaning making
into the scientific worldview do I see
them doing with that not that much
because here's what you have to here's
what you have to struggle with that
scientific worldview is deeply
undermining and it has been doing it for
centuries and I've made an argument at
length about this on this series I'm not
going to repeat it here it's been
undermined
the two world mythos of the axial
revolution that gave us an explanation
of how our wisdom and meaning making
fits into the fabric of reality and gave
us guidance and right legitimated our
practices that Axial Age 2 world
mythology is disappearing and I do not
see any of the religions providing a
answer to it or not I'm talking with
people again I want to be really careful
here like I'm talking with you know you
know JP Marceau and Mary Cohan right and
some of the work that paul banach lee I
see people individual Christians
triprotic trying to say can we let's try
and break out of the two world mythology
and come up with an alternative ontology
that might work
I see individuals doing that do I see
Christianity as a whole doing that or
Buddhism as a whole doing that no and
this helps to explain another important
fact so here's two people I've met one
personally he's got to have dinner with
them the other that's Stephen bachelor
the other is a deep you know you know
he's a friend of mine and you know
somebody I deeply respect and you know
he's a former colleague of mine at U of
T nuts Evan Thompson Stephen Bachelor
has written a book after Buddhism etham
Thompson has written a book why I'm not
a Buddhist precisely for these kinds of
arguments they do not they cannot find
within Buddhist modernism write anything
that addresses this concern that I've
just raised and these are deeply
sensitive deeply deeply people have
practiced deeply dedicated their lives
right you know these are not these are
not external critics or dilettante and
these are people of deep integrity
people who have you know we're deeply
identified with or at least deeply
friendly to Buddhism making this point
so that's what my concern is that also
helps to explain why I think for many
people it's one of the fastest-growing
demographics the nuns enno NES the
established religions don't have an
answer
because how they sort of mesh with
without getting into sort of magical new
agey kind of thinking how religions mesh
with the scientific worldview measure
measure would mesh with this hyper
technology and mesh with the way the
science and the hyper technology are on
ways that were often not even very aware
or aware of fundamentally altering our
cognition I don't see them I don't see
that being done and so I think that's
why the nuns are in that why that number
is increasing increasing so one more
point on this isn't is a point that I've
made in a recent discussion with Jordan
Hall was a private discussion that
Jordan gave me permission to talk about
it answering that question means
reformulating our thinking in a
fundamental way to get us out of the
kind of thinking that has put us into
the problems that we are facing right
now this that we are facing such
dramatic threats that we have to think
in a dramatic way and I think in a deep
sense we have to realize in a
dramatically different way than we have
before and it's unclear that we have the
timescale that the established religions
typically take in order to make that
kind of fundamental transformation Paul
very clay has made a very good point in
other ways he uses it as they think of
legitimate criticism against some of my
ideas which is you know religions take a
long time to change because they're very
conservative because you don't want to
you know it's hard fought and hard-won
wisdom and you you don't give it up
easily and you don't just go with any
new flashy idea that's true and that
means that religions are very
conservative and very slow in their
capacity to change and we don't have the
time we don't have the luxury of that
time so what is normally I would I would
deeply agree with Paul what is normally
a very adaptive
feature of religions is one that in this
context is maladaptive and let's
remember every adaptation necessarily
has context in which it will be
maladaptive so that's my answer to that
question that's why I don't think the
current religions are going to be right
solutions on mass again there's two
different versions of that question and
I've tried to answer them separately and
I would appreciate and I'm requesting
that people do not confuse those
together I've clearly said that I think
that the individual religions sorry
religions could give people individual
and legitimate in that sense responses
to the mean graces but here's my reasons
for suspecting that the existing
religions cannot now one final point
about that that is not a deductively
certain argument I have not given an
argument that forecloses on religion I
mean I could only do that if I had a
comprehensive and complete theory of
religion I do not have such a theory
I suspect that no one does so Jonathan
pooja for example to bring another
person of import into this thinks that
Christianity is going through such a
transformation right now I disagree with
him for the reasons I've given you but I
respect Jonathan enough to say he might
be right my argument does not foreclose
on his proposal so I've given you an
argument as to why I suspect he's wrong
but that's all it is that's all it is
anyone I think who tries to make
comprehensive conclusive absolute claims
about religion is presupposing that they
have an understanding of it that I
seriously doubt any human being does
here's another question for Mackenzie
Lovett
patreon supporter what most excites you
about your new series on authentic
dialogue wow that's such a great
question because there's so many things
so what's most exciting
I'm just learning so much I'm just
learning so much and as you know as a
kind of a geeky guy that just that just
really really like ah that's just been
so it's and learning so much about
something that I you know about
something that I find so profound which
is you know the processes by which
communication and transformation and ask
for aspiration occurred and I'm learning
a lot about a person who's you know a
hero for me the sage that I try to
internalize Socrates so all that has
just been like wow you know oh ma
and candy my candy so that's just been
fantastic secondly what's really been
exciting is taking up a lot of these new
practices and getting to meet the people
that are doing it and getting involved
in these discussions and actually
feeling the power of do logos and
starting to see the possibility of a
psycho technology dialectic that can
really help us you know get more coupled
to the dynamics of the logos and enhance
them so that we can access an exact
collective intelligence into collective
rationality into collective wisdom so
that we have that meta psycho technology
that will give us ways of you know of
guiding how we create and curate our
communities and our ecologies of
practices and that that right when you
when you go from ideas to practice and
you start to feel the power of these
practices and again not just in the in
the power of conviction how they're
giving you new beliefs but the power and
how they're actually reshaping
like your your perspectival and
participatory knowing even is shaping
your skills it's deeply impressive right
think of the word impressive I'm
noticing that I like even when I'm
teaching that I think we're back to the
percolation point that these practices
that I've been engaging with guy and
Jordan and with Chris and you know and
other things with especially all the
stuff I've been doing with peter
lindbergh and some of stuff gonna be
done I'm gonna be doing also with Edwin
on empathy circling right that those
things are like they percolate into you
and and they start to transform your
salience landscaping and the way you
feel sort of coupled and connected and
the way you can get into sort of mindset
resonance with and I notice all of that
shifting and I'm even noticing how much
more this is like a normative awakening
how much more I came up in my lecture
yesterday how much more the the
normativity of the
of dialogue of dialectical thinking of
being in dialogue how much I'm coming to
see how much more valuable that is then
just monologic you know argumentation
I'm really sensing like oh yes I see why
I see how in dialogue I can Wed
theorization two you know emotional in
you know involvement and identification
you know infuse plato's terms I can sort
of I can integrate reason with spirit
because I can bring the normativity of
truth and falsity into proper
integration with the normativity of
being a cultural being so the cultural
cognitive machinery is more properly
accessed and dialogue and dialectic than
just in monologue and treatise and so in
that that's going from being an idea to
something that I can feel its fingers
shaping the normativity of my discourse
and a my teaching and even the way I'm
relating to people and being able to
understand them and resonate with them
and that is just so deeply deeply
exciting and so you know when you're
when you can taste you know we can taste
from the depths of your being something
that can write in the depths of people's
face-to-face meeting with others you
know give them a way of you know
ameliorating self-deception and opening
up connected the connectedness that is
so central to meeting life when you can
actually taste that that's so that's so
exciting
it's so rewarding so thank you very much
for that
that wonderful question and I want to
thank again I tried to mention as many
people as a kid all the people that I
mentioned you know there have been
teaching me and practicing with me and
guiding me and are there with me like
Peter Lindbergh you know companions on
the way up just so much IOC the
transformative experience you cannot
horse you cannot defer and imagine your
way through it until you are already an
equivocally swept up within it and so so
much gratitude for them so much thank
you very much
oh I want to now thank to patreon
subscribers and everyone watching right
now as always your support is really
crucial to continuing to produce of
videos and supporting the science that's
going into addressing the meaning crisis
I want to one time mention again and it
follows exactly on the answer I gave to
that previous question the new series
that's coming out after Socrates the
pursuit and cultivation of wisdom
through authentic dialogue so pick up on
some of these themes and hopefully
you'll you'll get a better sense and
better reason and evidence for my
enthusiasm for this project of trying to
get a deep understanding of ancient
dialectic as for something that was in
to write in conversation but also
between people and reality and
transformation and aspiration and how
that ancient template can give us
something by which we can shape carve
ado straw out and improve these emerging
practices of authentic dialogue and
relating and give us something that is I
think plausibly what Jordan Hall is
asking for when he's asking for the meta
psycho technology I also want to remind
you of the IndieGoGo campaign for the
book the cognitive continuum from
insight to enlightenment please take a
look at both the short video and the
long video and I ask for your support I
want to remind you once more I am NOT
going to draw any income from either the
campaign or the book any income from the
book is going into the verb a key
foundation the money from the campaign
is going to support Daniel in his work
on the book and it's
excellent work on it exists it's been a
great pleasure and great gift to work
with Daniel on this so I please ask for
you to consider that and consider
supporting it so I want to turn to now a
couple of questions that are coming in
live so here's one for Cara Mia Cynthia
Clayton Thank You Cara Mia
I know I've noticed some of your
comments on my videos and I appreciate
them so thank you again for your
involvement and your support and your
engagement the question is what are your
latest ideas for lessening the meaning
crisis through a religion that's not a
religion so I mean part of it goes
towards what I was just talking about
some of my most recent ideas about are
about trying to get this meta secular
technology going and activate collective
intelligence and exempt it into
collective rationality and collective
wisdom and that's gonna have an
antibiotic and analogic a de pls
symbolic and aspirational aspect to it
so in that sense I and I know this
because I'm even involved in circling
practices and some of these practices
that's gonna have a kind of very
religious feel to it even though it's
not going to be dedicated towards sort
of some prototypical features of many
religions and it's not going to be based
on the ontology of those existing
religions so that's one thing the other
thing is there's a bunch of ideas that
are coming out right now and I'm going
to ask for some patience on this because
they're actually emerging in my ongoing
discussion with Jordan Hall so Jordan
and I had a recent conversation it's
specifically on the religion that's not
a religion and some of the powerful
ideas that were coming out of that
discussion we're not prepared yet to
release that publicly we're going to
have a couple more discussions and then
come back and and release that I would
point you to something else I had an
excellent
I'm very grateful to a conversation with
Andrew Sweeney about this it's going to
come out on his channel and it he asked
me a bunch of excellent questions about
the religion that's not a religion and
because I'm running out of time here
there was a long I had a much longer
space there and forum and it was
dialogic because he was asking me
questions and probing in which I try to
answer that question in depth so I'm
giving you I'm trying not to do a
cop-out here I'm saying there's a place
you can go to look at those ideas
Andrews going to release the video
shortly I believe Angelus also written a
really good commentary on medium about
my arguments and ideas about the
religion they're not religion that's
already up there I recommend you go
there and take a look at that and then
in addition to that the promise that
Jordan Hall and I are going to shortly
in the future again in dialogue format
release a video about getting much
clearer about what we mean what we're
talking about and some newer ideas in
connection that with that I want to
remind people something that I keep
saying we're not trying to found a
religion or anything like that please
that is not what is going on neither are
we trying to destroy any existing
religions there is something happening
right now there are emerging communities
of practice and they often approached me
because they hope that the work I've
done can help them to communicate to
train to connect with other such
communities and instead of just doing
that sort of haphazard it's the ideas
like no no can we do this in a highly
reflective fashion can I do it in
conjunction with some of the brightest
and best and committed minds on this can
I do it in conjunction with this project
about you know dialectic and deal logos
so that we can perhaps guide and like
this emerging process so that it can
address the meeting crisis more
comprehensively and more effectively and
hopefully also right thereby also
provide a community network of
communities in which we can start to
also as we resolve issues around meaning
start to bring wisdom to the problems in
the world right now that are exigent
that's the project so please understand
it that way so another question seen any
good movies lately um yeah I have I went
with my two cents or recently to see
19:17 and I was deeply impressed movies
that really impressed me are movies in
which there's this wonderful consonant
between the use of the format and the
content of the movie and the message of
the movie so like Lawrence of Arabia is
a prototypical example of that
you know David Lee just did this amazing
thing and what I found was something
analogous in 1917 that I liked so they
have this thing that's it's a little bit
of a it's write it if there's a little
bit of manipulation but it's right
you're it's like it's a continuous shot
it's like real time continuous shot and
so you're following these two characters
around right in real time as like in a
continuous shot and when what that does
is it gives you this immersive thing it
right so you know we there's a
temptation with world wars to step back
and think of a Nebraska all the problem
we do that is we turn off a lot of this
with cognitive science research shows
right we turn off a lot of our moral and
empathetic machinery when we move to
this high level of control
instead what 1917 is doing is keeping
you really immersed so you're not
standing back and reflecting on you're
actually being present in a
participatory way within the situation
and you know and so you're deeply
engaged with this so what's happening of
course is you get a lot of effective
responses because you know there's
there's moments of fear there's moments
of heroism and you're getting all of
that going on well of course or not I'm
not going to speak about specific stuff
because I don't want to do any spoilers
but that immersive right presencing and
infective and engagement is
put you face-to-face and try to really
hear what I'm saying I said put you
face-to-face with the deep absurdity of
trench warfare and World War one and
what it says about even when I was
talking about earlier about the deep a
measurement of Science and Technology
into the guts and fabric and the deaths
of our lives I the Titanic death and the
absurdity of it and to think that World
War one wasn't amassed with science and
technology and that World War one didn't
dramatically change the cultural
cognitive grammar of Europe I think is
to be naive and so in 1917 I think is a
beautiful movie that work of art for
conveying you into that and then can
through that conveying that message to
you so I highly recommend it I hope that
it's not a movie that you enjoy that's
the wrong verb but it's a move it's a
it's a work of art that draws from you
and gets you to think and understand and
even have your sensibility transformed
to a significant degree so here's a
question from Rice classroom Twitter you
speak about having and being modes and
we often try to solve beam problems with
having load approaches do people also
try to solve having modes having
problems from the beam oh yes they do
and I mean so there's some one comic
sometimes but they can be tragic and you
can get instances of this in therapy
where people need to do some very having
mode things they need to go out you know
let's say this is only meant to be one
example they need to get a job they need
to get a job
all right they need to have financial
resources so that they can feed and take
care of them so they need to do that and
instead of doing that they go into this
metaphysical abstraction about Who am I
and what am I and what's ultimately real
and what is a good human life these are
all questions of course that should be
asked they are being more questions but
when
people are asking those questions as a
way of actually avoiding the concrete
practical task of getting a job and
getting food because you need to have a
job and have food they can often get
stuck and they can get stuck in kind of
a Peter Pan situation where they're
always contemplating all the
metaphysical possibilities of who and
what they could be there I have so much
potential I could be this I could be
that I could be I could have this life I
could have that and there are they don't
want to kill any of the possibilities
but decision means to cut and at some
point you have to stop glorying in all
of the possibilities and actually do
something that's of course why we have
the myth of Peter Pan all right you
can't live in Neverland you can't be
listen to language a lost boy forever
and so it is very possible to have a
mode of confusion in which you're
treating having problems from the being
mode thank you very much for joining me
in this Q&A again excellent questions I
hope I strive to do good service to
these excellent questions
we're going we're doing is every third
Friday of the month we'll be back on
schedule next month I had some personal
issues that require that we moved things
and I appreciate everybody's patience
and understanding about that reminder
once again about patreon support I'm not
drawing any income from it it is
supporting the science is supporting the
video series it's supporting the work
we're doing the IndieGoGo campaign same
things not I'm not drawing an income for
it it's supporting a project that's
beneficial to a lot of people and I want
to thank all the supporters on patreon
and you can of course support my work on
the meaning crisis by going to
patreon.com/scishow on for baekje thank
you very much everyone for your time and
attention I look forward to interacting
with you again